When I turned 19, I started my career
عندما بلغت التاسعة عشر، بدأت حياتي المهنية
as the first female photojournalist
كأول أنثي تعمل كمصورة صحفية
in the Gaza Strip, Palestine.
في قطاع غزة في فلسطين.
My work as a woman photographer
عملي كمصورة إمرأة
was considered a serious insult
كان يعتبر إهانة حقيقة
to local traditions,
للعادات المحلية
and created a lasting stigma
مما جعلها وصمة عار أبدية
for me and my family.
لي و لعائلتي.
The male-dominated field made my presence
سيطرة الذكور على هذا المجال جعلت وجودي
unwelcome by all possible means.
غير مرحب به على الإطلاق.
They made clear that a woman
أعلنوها بوضوح أن المرأة
must not do a man's job.
لا يمكن أن تتخذ عمل الرجل.
Photo agencies in Gaza refused to train me
وكالات التصوير في غزة رفضت تدريبي
because of my gender.
فقط لجنسي.
The "No" sign was pretty clear.
علامة "لا" كانت واضحة.
Three of my colleagues
ثلاثة من زملائي
went as far as to drive me to an open air strike area
تمادوا لدرجة أنهم ذهبوا بي إلى منطقة قصف جوي مفتوح
where the explosion sounds
حيث يكون صوت الإنفجارات
were the only thing I could hear.
الشيء الوحيد الذي اسمعه.
Dust was flying in the air,
الغبار كان يتطاير في الهواء،
and the ground was shaking like a swing beneath me.
والأرض كانت كالأرجوحة تحتي.
I only realized we weren't there to document the event
لاحظت وقتها أننا لم نكن هناك لتوثيق الحدث
when the three of them got back into the armored Jeep
عندما عاد الثلاثة إلى سيارة الجيب المدرعة
and drove away, waving and laughing,
ثم قادوها بعيدا وهم يلوحون لي ويضحكون،
leaving me behind in the open air strike zone.
تاركينني في منطقة القصف المفتوح.
For a moment, I felt terrified,
للوهلة، شعرت بالذعر
humiliated, and sorry for myself.
والإهانة والأسف على نفسي.
My colleagues' action was not
تصرف زملائي لم يكن التهديد الوحيد الذي تلقيته
but it was the most dangerous one.
وإنما أكثرهم خطورة.
The perception of women's life in Gaza
مفهوم حياة المرأه في غزة
is passive.
سلبي.
Until a recent time, a lot of women were not allowed
حتي وقت قريب، لم يكن يسمح لكثير من النساء
to work or pursue education.
العمل أو طلب العلم.
At times of such doubled war including
في أوقات هذه الحرب المزدوجة التي تشمل
both social restrictions on women
القيود المجتمعية على المرأة
and the Israeli-Palestinian conflict,
والصراع الإسرئيلي-الفلسطيني،
women's dark and bright stories were fading away.
قصص النساء المظلمة والمضيئة كانت تختفي.
To men, women's stories were seen
للرجال، قصص المرأة بدت
as inconsequential.
غير مهمة.
I started paying closer attention
بدأت اهتم أكثر بملاحظة
to women's lives in Gaza.
حياة المرأة في غزة.
Because of my gender, I had access
لجنسي، تمكنت من الدخول
to worlds where my colleagues were forbidden.
إلى عالم محرم على زملائي.
Beyond the obvious pain and struggle,
خلف الألم والمعاناة الواضحة،
there was a healthy dose
كانت هناك جرعة صحية من المرح و والإنجازات.
In front of a police compound in Gaza City
أمام مجمع شرطة في مدينة غزة
during the first war in Gaza,
خلال الحرب الأولى في غزة،
an Israeli air raid managed to destroy the compound
غارة جوية إسرائيلية تمكنت من تدمير المجمع
and break my nose.
وكسر أنفي.
For a moment, all I saw was white, bright white,
للوهلة، كل ما رأيته هو اللون أبيض، أبيض ساطع،
like these lights.
كهذه الأنوار.
I thought to myself I either got blind
ظننت أني قد عميت
or I was in heaven.
أو أنني في الجنة.
By the time I managed to open my eyes,
مع مرور الوقت تمكنت من فتح عيناي،
I had documented this moment.
وقد وثّقت هذه اللحظة.
Mohammed Khader, a Palestinian worker
محمد خاضر، عامل فلسطيني،
who spent two decades in Israel,
أمضى عقدين من الزمن في إسرائيل،
as his retirement plan,
و قبل تقاعده،
he decided to build a four-floor house,
قرر بناء بيت من أربع طوابق،
only by the first field operation at his neighborhood,
وعند أول عملية ميدانية في حيه السكني،
the house was flattened to the ground.
تساوى المنزل بالأرض.
Nothing was left but the pigeons he raised
لم يتبقي شيء سوى الحمام الذي كان يربيه
and a jacuzzi, a bathtub
وجاكوزي (حوض استحمام)
that he got from Tel Aviv.
أتى به من تل أبيب.
Mohammed got the bathtub
وضع محمد حوض الاستحمام
on the top of the rubble
فوق أنقاض منزله
and started giving his kids
و بدأ يجعل أولاده
an every morning bubble bath.
يتسحموا فيه كل صباح.
My work is not meant to hide the scars of war,
عملي هو ليس إخفاء ندبات الحرب،
but to show the full frame
و لكن نقل الصورة الكاملة لها
of unseen stories of Gazans.
من قصص غير مرئية لأهل غزة.
As a Palestinian female photographer,
كمصورة وأنثي فلسطينية.
the journey of struggle, survival and everyday life
رحلة المعناه والبقاء والحياة اليومية
has inspired me to overcome the community taboo
ألهمتني لأتغلب على محظورات مجتمعي
and see a different side of war and its aftermath.
ورؤية جانب آخر من الحرب وتوابعها.
I became a witness with a choice:
أصبحت شاهدة ذات خيار:
to run away or stand still.
إما الهرب أو الصمود.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)